<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short way to a lasting settlement shewing, I. that parliaments are not infallible, II. who are their great enemies, III. how to redeem their reputation : with a warning to all loyal gentlemen and freeholders, in a letter to fanaticus ignoramus.</title>
            <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66903</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12734123</idno>
  <idno type="VID">66529</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240966111</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3351</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20374</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12734123</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66903)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66529)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 994:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short way to a lasting settlement shewing, I. that parliaments are not infallible, II. who are their great enemies, III. how to redeem their reputation : with a warning to all loyal gentlemen and freeholders, in a letter to fanaticus ignoramus.</title>
                  <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>"Attributed to Womock by Halkett &amp; Laing". cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Church and state --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Royal supremacy (Church of England)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66529:1"/>
            <p>A SHORT WAY TO A <hi>Lasting Settlement:</hi> SHEWING,
<list>
                  <item>I. That Parliaments are not Infallible.</item>
                  <item>II. Who are Their great Enemies.</item>
                  <item>III. How to Redeem their Reputation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>WITH A WARNING TO ALL Loyal Gentlemen AND Freeholders, In a LETTER to <hi>Fanaticus Ignoramus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:66529:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66529:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>Short VVay</hi> TO A Lasting Settlement.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Perceive you are soon mov'd into Passion, and can grow Angry upon such a score as will much more reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your self, and the <hi>Party</hi> you have espoused. You pretend I am <hi>an Enemy to Parliaments;</hi> When really I am a much more hearty friend to them, than they are, or you your self, as shall be clearly Demonstrated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I take leave of you.</p>
            <p>But I desire you to consider well what you mean by the word <hi>Parliament,</hi> that you may not (as too many <hi>Zealots</hi> do) mistake the Word for the Thing it self. The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> is the Assembly of the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Three Estates</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, (which are the Lords <hi>Spiritual,</hi> the Lords <hi>Temporal,</hi> and the <hi>Commons</hi>) to debate matters of emergent Difficulty touching the <hi>Common-Weal;</hi> and to decide and settle them by mature ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the best advantage thereof.</p>
            <p>Now the King being the <hi>Head</hi> of this Parliament (without whom it cannot so much as have a being, in the right Notion and true Nature of a Parliament) I hope I shall not be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an <hi>Enemy,</hi> at least to His <hi>Majesty,</hi> having served Him and his <hi>Royal</hi> Father of ever Blessed Memory, as well in the times of War as Peace, for Forty years together.</p>
            <p>Take a Parliament in the right Notion and just Constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66529:3"/> of it; and I am ready to Subscribe to the sence of that great <hi>States-Man,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> in the Character he gives<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Repub. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glor.</hi> l. 2. c. 2.</note> of this Supream Court, <q>
                  <hi>In comitiis Parliamentariis,</hi> &amp;c. The most high and absolute Power of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth in the Parliament; for the Parliament abrogateth old Laws, maketh New, giveth Order for things past, and for things hereafter to be followed; changeth the Rights and Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessions of private Men; Legitimateth Bastards, Corroborates Religion by Civil Sanctions, Alters Weights and Measures; <hi>Prescribes and determines the Right of Succession to the Crown,</hi> defines doubtful Rights where there is no Law already made, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> The Wisdom and Learning of the Kingdom supposed, in a great Measure, to be Assembled here, the Parliament may very well be able to resolve and assign, where <hi>The Right of Succession is,</hi> in doubtful Cases; But they can no more make a <hi>just Title</hi> of a <hi>bad One,</hi> or a <hi>lawful Prince</hi> of an <hi>Ʋsurper,</hi> than they can make a Man a Woman.</p>
            <p>The King (we say, and the <hi>Law</hi> sayes so too) <hi>can do no wrong:</hi> But 'twas never said so of the <hi>Three Estates</hi> of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And if these do amiss, surely, I may justly be displeas'd at them, when they do so, and yet be no enemy to the Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. I may blame my Child, my Wife, and yet have a very tender Affection for them. But we must remember 'tis the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly <hi>Entire,</hi> and made up of all its <hi>Constituent</hi> Parts that we must value. Divide the <hi>Estates</hi> from their <hi>Head,</hi> or from <hi>one another,</hi> and you dissolve the Government. And when they are well <hi>Ʋnited,</hi> and act <hi>regularly</hi> by common Suffrage and Consent, yet they are not inspired, they Act as men, and we are to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute no more to them, we are to expect no more from them, then to and from a <hi>Humane Constitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Author you alleadge, seems to make a Parliament <hi>Infallible;</hi> else how can he so confidently alleadge what they have done, to Evince the <hi>Legality</hi> of whatever they shall do hereafter? Does Matter of <hi>Fact</hi> always conclude a certain <hi>Right?</hi> He is a very ill <hi>Logician</hi> that so argues. For if this Rule were granted, the blackest Villanies that Hell can invent or hatch, such as have fill'd the Age that did them with shame and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, may be defended; all the most execrable Rebellions, U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surpations, Deposings of Princes, and Regicides, that have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66529:3"/> been Committed or done by Parliaments, even by that of <hi>Forty-One</hi> are to be justifyed; and not only so, but become fair <hi>Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> to encourage the like hereafter. And to this purpose are all those <hi>Precedents</hi> produced by the <hi>Tory-Plot-Maker</hi> to destroy <hi>Successten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if all that a Parliament does (that is, the <hi>Prime</hi> with the assent of the <hi>Three Estates</hi>) be warrantable, just and good, then the establishment of <hi>Popery</hi> in the dayes of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was so too; and this Gentleman, who is so good at alledging <hi>Precedents,</hi> may be as well furnished perhaps with precedents on that side, if he had occasion for it. But if that were ill done by Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and her Parliament, it follows undeniably, that all Parliamentary proceedings are not warrantable, nor their Acts to be drawn into example.</p>
            <p>The Gentleman should distinguish betwixt a Power that is <hi>Ʋncontroulable,</hi> and that which is <hi>Infallible.</hi> An Uncontroula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Power may be damnably Wicked, (so was <hi>Cromwels:</hi>) but an <hi>Infallible</hi> Power cannot be so. Indeed an <hi>Ʋncontroulable</hi> Power can <hi>take no wrong</hi> (while it continues uncontroulable:) but an <hi>Infallible</hi> Power <hi>can do none.</hi> A Parliament, because it is the <hi>Supream Court,</hi> is not Subject to <hi>Coercion;</hi> but for all that, it may do great, very great Injustice, and so be very blameable upon that account. If they were <hi>Infallible,</hi> what need such can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vassing at <hi>Elections,</hi> and at <hi>Committees</hi> about them afterwards? Why such shuffling and cutting to Pack the <hi>Cards,</hi> and get a suit of Members into the House, to make sure our own Game? 'Tis but sitting down in their seats (as the <hi>Pope</hi> does in his Chair) and pass a <hi>Vote,</hi> and the business is done. All is just, if They be <hi>Infallible:</hi> But God knows 'tis far otherwise. This is Solemnly acknowledged by the Lord <hi>Hollis</hi> in his last <hi>Effort,</hi> and he cites Law for it in his <hi>Remaines</hi> (p. 60.) where He saith, <q>The Authority of any one Parliament I know to be very great, yet it is a known Maxime in the Law, <hi>Parliament poit Errer,</hi> A Parliament may err; and another Parliament may mend, what one doth amiss; Parliament-Men are Men, and may and do sometimes Mistake as well as other Men. Thus that Lord<note place="margin">Of Judicat. in Parl. <hi>P.</hi> 22.</note> hath ingenuously acknowledged; and Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> tells us, that <hi>Anne Peirce</hi> was unjustly convicted in a Parliament of 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. and that the then <hi>Speaker</hi> of the <hi>Commons</hi> did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess it.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:66529:4"/>
            <p>But to come neerer home to our selves; A Party in both <hi>Houses</hi> had a Design to take away the Life of the Earl of <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford;</hi> but their Evidence was not sufficient in a judicial way, and according to the due Forms of Law. <q>Hereupon they call in the <hi>Legislative</hi> Power to their Assistance; That they might proceed against him by the light of their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, without any further Proof or Testimony. But know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what dangerous consequence it might be hereafter, to the Lives and Fortunes of themselves and their Posterity; They added a <hi>Clause</hi> to the <hi>Bill,</hi> that it should not be drawn into example hereafter.</q>
               <hi>Habemus Legem;</hi> We have a Law, <hi>and by that Law He ought to Die.</hi> The very Malice of the <hi>Jews</hi> could admit of so much Justice: But <hi>feramus Legem,</hi> Let us <hi>Make</hi> a [New] <hi>Law,</hi> to take away his Life; <hi>This is little less than Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</hi> And whether it be a greater instance of Injustice to Suborn Witnesses to Prove a deadly Crime against the <hi>Innocent;</hi> Or, to <hi>Frame</hi> a New Law on purpose to make him <hi>Guilty,</hi> I shall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine: But sure I am, the late <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> of Blessed Memory,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. on the Earl of <hi>Straffords</hi> Death.</note> suffer'd much in the <hi>Remorse of Conscience,</hi> for passing that <hi>Bill</hi> into a <hi>Law,</hi> as is evident in his <hi>Divinest Meditations.</hi> Having reckoned up the <hi>Heads</hi> of his Accusation, They Enact, <hi>That he stand adjudged and attainted of High Treason, that he shall suffer Death, and forfeit all his Goods and Chattels, Lands and Tenements,</hi> &amp;c. But then, as a <hi>Conviction</hi> of their own <hi>injustice</hi> in the Case, they add this Clause: viz. <hi>Provided that no Judge, or Judges, Justice or Justices what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, shall adjudge or interpret any Act or Thing to be Treason, nor hear or determine any Treason, nor in any other manner, then he or they should or ought to have done before the making of this Act, and as if this Act had never been made.</hi> Thus have we <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi>
               <note place="margin">Observat. on the History of the Reign of K. <hi>Charles</hi> p. 231. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and no <hi>Treason</hi> in the self-same action; that being judged <hi>Treason</hi> in this one man, which never was to be judged <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> in any other, as Dr. <hi>Heylen</hi> well observes.</p>
            <p>Besides, we know the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> yea and the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> alone, nay a part, the <hi>worst</hi> and most <hi>factious</hi> part of them, have <hi>usurpt</hi> the power of all the <hi>Three Estates,</hi> and then <hi>Depos'd</hi> and <hi>Murdred</hi> their Prince; and shall any Subject dare to assert this to be <hi>Justifyable;</hi> and alledge that it has been done; and therefore 'tis Lawful to do't again? yet this is the Sum of that doubty Argument which that Loyal <hi>Gentleman</hi> so much triumphs in.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:66529:4"/>
            <p>If you talk of <hi>Real Enemies</hi> to Parliaments, certainly they are the worst and greatest, who turn <hi>them</hi> into <hi>Idols,</hi> affect and Admire them beyond the measure of a <hi>Humane-Creature,</hi> and commit at least, such <hi>Civil Idolatry</hi> with them, as makes them not only suspected to aspire above the <hi>Spheare</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentatives:</hi> but really to become a <hi>Burden</hi> to Prince and People, and indeed a greater <hi>Grievance</hi> than any they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted or intrusted to redress.</p>
            <p>'Tis not to be denyed, the Parliament is the <hi>Supream-Court</hi> of the Kingdom, (when they are in conjunction with their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign) and therefore <hi>uncontroulable</hi> while they are so: But when they act against their Prince, the fundamental Laws, and the establisht Government, then they are not the <hi>Supreme-Court:</hi> but a <hi>Faction,</hi> that sets up it self against it: And tho their Numbers and Combinations may make them <hi>uncontroulable</hi> and secure for a time, yet really they are not unaccountable either before God or man; and I am sure 'tis an ill Precedent to the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of Authority to let them finally goe unpunished.</p>
            <p>How undutiful and uneasie they have been to their <hi>Soveraigns,</hi> is not to be reported in these Papers, because not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised in fo short a <hi>Pamphlet</hi> as I design to publish. But that Learned <hi>Divine</hi> and Great <hi>Historian</hi> of a deep and piercing judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Heylen</hi> Observat. on the Hist. of the Raign of K. <hi>Charles.</hi> Pag. 28. Printed 1656.</note> has a witty observation upon <hi>King James.</hi> Our Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niclers saith He, tells us of King <hi>James,</hi> that at his first coming to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi>
               <q>He used to go often to the <hi>Tower,</hi> to see the <hi>Lyon</hi> (the reputed King of Beasts) baited, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by <hi>Doggs,</hi> and sometimes by <hi>Horses;</hi> which I could never read, saith He, without some regret; the baiting of the King of Beasts seeming to me an ill Presage of those many baitings, which He (a King of Men) found afterwards at the hands of His Subjects.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>baitings</hi> of that King of happy Memory was but <hi>Sport</hi> in comparison of what his <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Successor, Charles</hi> the first suffered under them. And I shall content my self in tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing some few particulars of the Account that is given thereof, by that judicious and knowing <hi>Observator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never did any Prince so often <hi>Vail his Crown</hi> to his People; which (as he observes) served to no effect, but to make them the more insolent and imperious. After many indignities and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66529:5"/> provocations given him by the disorder and tumultuous Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of some Members (which you may read, very handsomly and ingenuously described at large, in Mr. <hi>H. L'estrange</hi> his<note place="margin">Of the Raign of K. <hi>Charles.</hi> fol. 132.</note>
               <hi>History</hi>) His Majesty was forced to dissolve that Parliament; and it seems it was the opinion of most men, that the <hi>dissolution</hi> of that Parliament, <hi>was the end of All:</hi>
               <q>And certainly, saith Dr. <hi>Heylyn,</hi> there was very good reason why it might be thought<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> P. 92, &amp;c.</note> so, the King never having good Success in any of his Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments, since his first coming to the Crown; and withall hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an example before his eyes, of the like discontinuance of assembling the <hi>Three Estates</hi> in the Realm of <hi>France,</hi> by the King then Reigning, and that upon far less provocations than were given King <hi>Charles.</hi> For whereas in an Assembly of the <hi>Three Estates Anno.</hi> 1614. the <hi>Third Estate,</hi> which represents our House of <hi>Commons,</hi> entrenched too busily upon the liberties of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and some preheminencies and exemptions which the Nobility enjoyed by the favour of some former Kings; it gave the King so great offence, that he resolved, first to <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve them,</hi> and never after to be troubled with the like <hi>Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencies.</hi> Nor was there since that time any such <hi>Assembly,</hi> nor like to be hereafter in the times ensuing; those Kings growing weary of that yoke, which that great <hi>Representative</hi> did endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to impose upon them. But because he would not cut off all communication betwixt himself and his people, he ordained another king of meeting in the place thereof, which he called <hi>La Assembli des Notables,</hi> that is to say, The Assembly of some Principal Persons; composed of some Selected Persons out of every <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Estate</hi> (of his own Nomination) whereunto should be added some Counsellor out of every Court of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, (of which there are eight in all in <hi>France</hi>) through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that Kingdome; which being fewer in number, would not breed such a confusion, as the general <hi>Assembly</hi> of the <hi>States</hi> had done before, and be withall more pliant and conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Kings desires; and yet their Acts to be no less obliging to all sorts of People than the other were. Such an Assembly as this (but that the <hi>Clergy</hi> had no vote in it) was that which was called here by the <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> immediately after the dissolving of the late long <hi>Parliament,</hi> who possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly had his hint from this <hi>Institution.</hi> And this may teach all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66529:5"/> Parliaments in the times Succeeding, to be more careful in their Councils, and use more moderation in pursuance of them; especially when they meet with an armed Power, for fear they should not only interrupt, but cut off that Spring, from whence the Blessings both of Peace and Happiness, have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been derived on this Church and State. No man can love his fetters tho they be of Gold. If therefore <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments</hi> should find no way to preserve the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the people, but to put fetters on the <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Power</hi> that calls them; if from being <hi>Counsellors,</hi> at the best they shall prove <hi>Controulers,</hi> they must blame no body but themselves in case they should be discontinued for the time to come. In the mean time that saying of <hi>Paterculus</hi> may be worth their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, <hi>Non turpe est ab eo vinci, quem vincere esset nefas;</hi> it is no shame to submit to those, whom it were sin to overcome.</q> Thus farr that discerning <hi>Doctor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How they used His Majesty in the Case of <hi>Ship-Money,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heylyn 18. P. 219.</note>
               <q>ought not to be forgotten; yet the opinion of the legality of it was so fixed in the minds of many understanding Men, that it could not easily be removed: 1. In regard of the great learning and integrity of the man, by whom it was first set on foot. 2. Because all the Judges had subscribed unanimously to the Lawfulness of it in time of danger, of which danger the King was declared to be the Judge. 3. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause being brought to a publick Trial, after it had been argued by the Councel on both sides, in the Court of Justice, and by all the Judges in the Exchequer-Chamber, there passed a definitive sentence for it on bahalf of the King 4. Because voted down by the Houses of Parliament in a more <hi>Arbitrary</hi> way, than was expected without being brought to a review, neither the Kings Councel being heard, nor the judges called to shew the Reasons of their Opinions. 5. Because it was ordered by the House of <hi>Commons,</hi> that the <hi>Arguments</hi> of Justice <hi>Crooke</hi> and Justice <hi>Hutton</hi> for the illegality there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of should be put in Print: those of the other Eight <note n="*" place="margin">These are now publisht in the <hi>Annals</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel</hi> 1681.</note> Judges which were for the legality of it, continuing suppressed; which gave occasion to most men to think, that there was more reason for it in those Arguments, then was thought fit to see the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66529:6"/> light. And last of all, because notwithstanding all this Care to Vote down this <hi>Assessment,</hi> they were fain to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to the King, for obtaining of an Act of Parliament to secure them from it for the time to come.</q> This we are obliged to that worthy <hi>Dr.</hi> for.</p>
            <p>But notwithstanding, they made it their business to incroach upon his Prerogative, His Majesty could not lay aside his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>party to be Gracious; and though some members of the House of <hi>Commons,</hi> in His <hi>Third</hi> Parliament, (being imprisoned for<note place="margin">Heylyn 16. p. 31.</note> the refusal of a loan) brought with them both a <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Will,</hi> to avenge themselves by the restraint of his Prerogative: yet was he so melted into tenderness by a Grant of some <hi>Subsidies,</hi> that he bid his Secretary tell them, <hi>He would deny them nothing of their Liberties, which any of his Predecessors had granted to them;</hi> and finally in the close thereof, He enacted the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> and made it pass into a Law: Of which that Historian tells us, <hi>That never Arbitrary Power since Monarchy</hi> (was) <hi>first foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>L'estrange.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>did so,</hi> Submittere fasces, <hi>so vail his Scepter; Never did the</hi> Prerogative, <hi>descend so much</hi> from perch to popular lure, as by that Concession.</p>
            <p>But having prevailed upon his goodness to take himself <hi>down thus low,</hi> they were resolved to keep him <hi>under;</hi> for, having brought him to this pass, saith my Author, how easily did they (through their importunity, or rather violence) gain from him several <hi>Acts,</hi> for suppressing the Authority of the <hi>Clerke of the Market,</hi> and the Court of <hi>Stanneries,</hi> for retrenching the<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. P. 248.</note> Preambulation of the Forrests, and repealing the old <hi>Acts</hi> for Knight-hood; and finally (not to say any thing of the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> with the <hi>Forts</hi> and <hi>Navy,</hi> wherein they had not his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent) with what a strong hand did they draw him to the abolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Ship-Money,</hi> the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> the <hi>High-Commission,</hi> the Courts of the <hi>Marquess</hi> on the North, the Jurisdiction of all the Ecclesiastical Courts, some priviledges formerly enjoyed by the Councel Table, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But this is not all: For,</p>
            <p>Having driven him away by Tumults, they endeavoured by Remonstrances, Declarations and Propositions, to make his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn impossible. In <hi>June</hi> 42. the faction sends a Petition with <hi>Nineteen</hi> Propositions to his Majesty, many of which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty declared he could neither in Honour or Conscience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66529:6"/> unto. One of which saith the Royal Martyr, (in his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the nineteen Propositions) was, <hi>To bind my self to a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and implicite Consent to whatever they shall desire or propound; which were as if</hi> Sampson <hi>should have consented not only to bind his own hands, and cut off his hair, but to put out his own eyes, that the</hi> Philistians <hi>might with the more safety mock and abuse him; which they chose rather to do, then quite to destroy him, when he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come so tame an Object, and fit occasion for their sport and scorn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by this time, the <hi>Faction</hi> (having drawn the Seditious part of the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> in to their <hi>Alliance</hi>) began to entitle themselves to a share in <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> and a <hi>Coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi>
               <note place="margin">Parem non habet Rex in Regno suo. Omnis sub eo est, &amp; ipse sub nullo nisi tantum sub Deo. Ea quae Jurisdictionis sunt &amp; pacis ad nullum perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, nisi ad coronam &amp; Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem Regiam, Nec a coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na separari possunt. <hi>Braction.</hi>
               </note> Power with His Majesty. And that, <hi>Coordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta se invicem supplent,</hi> such Powers as are <hi>Coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> may supply the defects of one another, being a most undoubted Maxime in the Schools of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick,</hi> the two Houses take upon them to act <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> the King, and <hi>against</hi> him; then a <hi>part</hi> of both Houses oppose the King and all the rest; and at last the <hi>Factious</hi> part of the <hi>Commons</hi> exclude the <hi>Lords.</hi> And to give themselves some Colour of Authority, (1648.) they pass this Vote, <hi>That the Representative of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Parliament have the Supream Power of the Nation: and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is enacted or declared for Law by the Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath the form of a Law; and the People are concluded thereby, tho the Consent of King and Peers be not had thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Because <hi>Coordinates</hi> can supply the place of one another; The two Houses take the Rule upon them without (and against) the King; Then a Part of both Houses: Then the Commons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the Lords. And having raised an Army and seized the <hi>Militia</hi> by Sea and Land, possest themselves of His Majesties Towns, Forts and Castles; and proving successful in their attempts, They presumed Their Power was incontroulable; and then They call the King to an account (<hi>Horresco referens,</hi>) tho the Law sayes, <hi>The Parliament may not give judgment against the King,</hi> If we may believe their Darling Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Instit. 2. v. Shep. Abridg. tit. prog. p. 52. The great point of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession Discus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, pag. 14.</note>: And there is good reason for it; For <hi>if the Breath of the Kings No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strils was necessary to give them their Being, it is a little irrational to suppose, they could thence derive a Lawful Power to destroy the Author of their life: besides</hi> (as a very, ingenious Person iargues)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66529:7"/>
               <hi>how can it be supposed they could proceed justly to pass a final sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon Him, whose concurrence was absolutely required to give birth to any Law which might concern His Meanest Subjects, tho they thought it never so convenient?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet such Doctrines were spread abroad by many of their <hi>Schismatical</hi> and <hi>Seditious</hi> Divines, especially by their <hi>Proud, Bold</hi> and <hi>Heady</hi> Chaplain Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> For, taking it for granted, that the <hi>Soveraign Power,</hi> by the Constitution of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is divided between the <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>Senate,</hi> (by which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presseth himself in many places of his Pamphlets and Writings,<note place="margin">See. The History of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration the 2d. part. pag. 11. 54, 55, &amp;c. passim.</note> to mean the House of <hi>Commons</hi>) He saith, <hi>That the Legislative Power being divided between a Prince and Senate, the Prince invading the Senates Right,</hi> (tho 'tis evident the Senate he pleads for were the <hi>Aggressors) may justly be resisted, and lose his Right;</hi> Nay and his life too; and he thinks they could never ingage an Army to defend them upon other terms. And these Doctrines do not drop from his Pen by chance and without advisement; for he repeats it over and over upon all occasions in his Writings, as you may find them collected to your hand in the Book mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Margent. <hi>If the body of a Commonwealth, or those that have part in the Legislative Power, and so in the Supremacy, should unwillingly</hi> (but the Faction he pleads for were designedly) <hi>ingaged in a Warr with the Prince, and after many years Blood and Desolation, judicially take away his Life, as guilty of all this Blood, and not to be trusted any more with Government; and all this they do not as private men, but as the remaining Soveraign Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and say they do according to the Laws:</hi> (and what Rebel or Traytor will not say so?) <hi>undoubtedly the case differs very much from Papists Murdering of Kings.</hi> If you be not already sick of this Seditious Doctrine, Ple give you a little more; He saith, <hi>That the Law that saith the King shall have the</hi> Militia, <hi>supposeth it to be against Enemies,</hi> (and are not Rebels and Traytors such;) <hi>and not against the Commonwealth, nor them that have a part in the Soveraignty; and to resist him here, is not to resist Power, but Ʋsurpation and private Will. And where the Soveraignty is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into several hands, as into King and Parliament, and the King invades the other part, they may lawfully defend their own by Warr, and the Subject lawfully assist them; yea tho the Power of the</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia <hi>be expressly given to the King, unless it be also expressed that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66529:7"/> it shall not be in the other.</hi> Holy Commonwealth. <hi>Thes.</hi> 363.</p>
            <p>And this Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> delivers not as his own single sense; for he tells us, <q>
                  <hi>Surely it was the Judgment of the Parliament</hi> (so he calls any thing that pretended to a Power to oppose the King) <hi>upon the division</hi> (between the King and them) the Power was in them to defend themselves and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and suppress all Subjects that were in Armes against them: and that those that did resist them, did resist the Higher Powers set over them by God, and therefore were guilty of the damnation of Resisters.</q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Quo teneam nodo.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>What Law or Gospel can secure the Rights or Life of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the <hi>Distinctions</hi> of this Seditious <hi>Casuist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Prince can be in love with any Parliament of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion? Wherefore They, who publisht such Doctrine, and make so close an Application and Use of it in their Practice, have the greater sin, and are the greatest <hi>Enemies</hi> to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>For our present <hi>Gracious Soveraign</hi> (whom God long preserve in health and happiness) their usage of him is fresh in every mans Memory. When the Lord return'd him from his <hi>Exile,</hi> then were we <hi>like unto them that Dream.</hi> All Loyal hearts were warm'd with joy, and the Factious Child with guilt, no less than with their old <hi>fears and jealousies.</hi> This kept them quiet awhile: but as soon as the <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> had secured them against those Fears, and the King had taken many of them into his warm Bosome, then the (lately <hi>benum'd</hi>) Serpent began to <hi>Hisse</hi> and shoot out his <hi>Sting</hi> anew. And being well read and practised in the Arts of Dissimulation and Wheadling, they soon felt how the <hi>Pulse</hi> beat in every <hi>Party,</hi> and began to work upon the <hi>Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of some, and the <hi>Discontents</hi> of others, whose Ambition or Avarice had met with disappointments.</p>
            <p>When they had mustred up their Numbers and came to know their own strength, then they began to strike up, <hi>The second Part to the same Tune of Forty One.</hi> And altho the <hi>Title</hi> was not <hi>now</hi> set up at the House of Commons <hi>Doore,</hi> as it was then; <hi>A King and no King;</hi> yet the <hi>Play</hi> was the very same, which they were Acting within (as many of us can very well remember) with the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66529:8"/> addition of some new <hi>Scenes</hi> and <hi>Actors.</hi> And so eager they were in the pursuit of their Design, they were resolv'd to sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice any thing to carry it on, as their own <hi>Votes</hi> and <hi>Speeches</hi> have inform'd us.</p>
            <p>What regard they had to the Honour of the Nation, we may esily Calculate from Their neglect of <hi>Tangier;</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation Whereof (considering the Circumstances 'twas in) was no less a <hi>Wonder</hi> than the <hi>Mole</hi> erected there; Which <hi>Divine Providence</hi> reserved for the Glory of His <hi>Majesty</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish.</p>
            <p>And whereas, of Antient times, it was no less the <hi>Generosity,</hi> than the Duty and Affection of <hi>English</hi> Subjects to raise their Contributions freely to support the <hi>Crown,</hi> now of late, through the insinuation and contrivance of men, These <hi>Aides</hi> and <hi>Subsidies</hi> are never granted, but to make a <hi>Merchandize</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>For they are afraid the burden of the Crown should oppress the <hi>English Liberties,</hi> (tho the truth is, <hi>These</hi> Liberties have<note place="margin">English Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> met with very favourable Seasons to shoot forth: and the Branches thereof have been <hi>Complicated</hi> and imbellisht with so much Artifice by a cunning hand, that they are come to a pretty Convenient <hi>Head,</hi> to emulate the Crown it self, if not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front it: And to make this <hi>Luxuriant</hi> Tree the more useful, every man, at the price of a single shilling, may have it Planted at his own door, to shelter him from almost all the Storms and Thunder of the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> and <hi>Coercive</hi> Government.) For all this, I say, They are afraid, the weight or dreeping influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the Crown should quench the growth of their <hi>English Liberties.</hi> Wherefore they attempt, as fast as they can, to pluck away the <hi>Massie</hi> Flowers of it; And filling up their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with sharp <hi>Crosses,</hi> They encircle it with a Wreath of <hi>thorny Cares,</hi> that it may sit uneasy upon their Princes Head, and make him the more willing to let them pull it off.</p>
            <p>Though it was our Saviours charge, that we should <hi>Render unto Caesar the things that are Caesars,</hi> pointing at the very <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute-Mony</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 6.</note> which bore the <hi>stamp of</hi> Caesars <hi>Image and Superscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> And tho the great Apostle accounts such Tribute a <hi>Debt,</hi> that belongs to Caesar <hi>as Gods Minister,</hi> to support the <hi>Charge</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of a Divine Vicegerency, yet our <hi>English Liberties</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:66529:8"/> teach us other things. We say the King can have none of our <hi>Estate</hi> without our own <hi>Consent:</hi> And to be sure, We have a <hi>Free-born-People,</hi> that will never give him their Consent to any <hi>Money-matter</hi> unless they see Good Reason for it. The <hi>Body<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politick</hi> is very apt to breed the <hi>Kings-Evil:</hi> His Majesty could heal it with a <hi>touch</hi> of his <hi>Prerogative,</hi> but 'tis Resolved, <hi>No Cure, No Mony;</hi> Nor indeed will they trust him, (who has the best Reason to know it) to judge of the <hi>Distemper.</hi> They know their own <hi>Grievances,</hi> and those are the things they are concern'd for.</p>
            <p>There is an odd <hi>Constitution</hi> called a Church, and this, they say, is a <hi>Divine</hi> Establishment; and the <hi>Godly party</hi> can make no <hi>Effort</hi> upon the Government by their <hi>Common-Wealth-Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples;</hi> but this <hi>Church-Party</hi> are ready to twit them for dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty, for <hi>Schism</hi> and <hi>Sedition;</hi> they cast them in the teeth with the Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and reproach them with the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Homilies against Rebellion. Verily this is a great grievance to the <hi>Godly-party.</hi> (tho the Prince Himself may think otherwise.)</p>
            <p>And indeed, <hi>Monarchy</hi> it self is the <hi>Sum Total</hi> of All <hi>that</hi> Party can complain of; and 'tis not long since they <hi>opposed</hi> it as a <hi>Grievance.</hi> And let us not believe they can so easily forget their old <hi>Sentiments.</hi> Can they ever travel with so Noble a <hi>Design</hi> as to make the Crown <hi>Flourish?</hi> No, no, They will do all they can to <hi>tarnish</hi> the Splendour, and <hi>wither</hi> the Beauty of it: They make it their business to shrink up the <hi>sinews</hi> of the Royal Power, and to <hi>Cripple</hi> the Government; And when by an obstinate denyal of all timely <hi>Aide,</hi> they can bring it to pass, that the King can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>stand</hi> without them, then they will <hi>set up themselves,</hi> and Govern in <hi>Aid</hi> of him (as the <hi>Spencers</hi> would have had it) and that shall be in lieu of all future <hi>Subsidies</hi> to their Prince. And to this end they will hang their own <hi>Arbitrary Padlocks</hi> upon our private Pockets, that whatever our Duty and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections may oblige or prompt us to, it may not be in our Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (if they can help it) to relieve our Prince in his greatest exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
            <p>If this be not the Design of that <hi>Party,</hi> what mean those<note place="margin">His Majesties Declaration. 1681.</note> endearing <hi>Votes</hi> of the seventh of <hi>January,</hi> 1681. as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:66529:9"/>
            <p>Resolved, <hi>That whosoever shall lend or cause to be lent by way</hi>
               <note place="margin">Here they put <hi>Padlocks</hi> upon our <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> and allow not a <hi>Dominion</hi> over our own <hi>Estates;</hi> is not this <hi>Arbitrary?</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>of Advance, any Money upon the Branches of the Kings Revenue, arising by Customes, Excise, or Hearth-Money, shall be adjudged to hinder the sitting of Parliaments, and shall be responsible for the same in Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Resolved, <hi>That whosoever shall buy any Tally of Anticipation upon any part of the Kings Revenue, or whosoever shall pay any such Tally hereafter to be struck; shall be adjudged to hinder the Sitting of Parliaments, and shall be responsible for the same in Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were not these very endearing Resolutions? What Prince would not hugg such a <hi>Dutiful</hi> House of <hi>Commons</hi> for them? That Party that could take the Confidence to pass such <hi>Votes</hi> about the <hi>Revenue</hi> of their Soveraign, without all questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would have <hi>seized</hi> it into their own hands, if their <hi>Associa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-Army</hi> had been ready for it.</p>
            <p>But notwithstanding all this, His Majesty is <hi>as an Angel of God,</hi> to discern betwixt a <hi>prevalent Faction,</hi> and the Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Three Estates</hi> duely qualified; and therefore he was pleased in His Gracious <hi>Declaration,</hi> to give us this Caution: <hi>Let not the restless Malice of Ill Men, who are labouring to poyson our people, (some out of fondness of their Old Beloved Commonwealth-Principles, and some out of anger at their being disappointed in the Particular Designes they had for the accomplishment of their own Ambition and Greatness) perswade any of our Good Subjects, that we intend to lay aside the use of Parliaments: For we do still De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That no Irregularities of Parliaments, shall ever make us out of love with Parliaments, which we look upon as the best Method for healing the Distempers of the Kingdom, and the only Means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the Monarchy in that due Credit and Respect, which it ought to have both at home and abroad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is his Majesties <hi>Gracious Declaration, Sense</hi> and <hi>Temper,</hi> and all Good Subjects will readily subscribe to it, and follow such a pattern.</p>
            <p>But for all this (being upon this inquiry) are not they <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> to Parliaments, who give the highest <hi>provocations</hi> that may be to set the <hi>Church</hi> against them? yet this hath been done by that <hi>Fanatick Party.</hi> After such great pretences and braggs of their own Care and Zeal for Religion, one would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66529:9"/> that (had they not laid down their estates at the Apost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les feet) they would have opened their purses and laid out (at least, as <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> did) some part of it, for osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; that they would have bought in all Impropriations, and laid them again to the Church for the encouragement of <hi>Orthodox</hi> and faithful Ministers: but we were egregiously delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this expectation. <q>The Rights and Priviledges of Holy<note place="margin">D. <hi>Heylyn</hi> Ib. <hi>p.</hi> 60.</note> Church, confirmed in the very first Article of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and sworne to by all Kings Succeeding, were never so infringed, as by that <hi>Act</hi> of Excluding the Bishops from sitting in the House of <hi>Peers:</hi> Where assuredly they had sate longer, in their Praedecessors, than any of the <hi>Lay-Nobility</hi> in their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest Ancestors; and had as good right of Sitting and Voting there, as either the Praerogative Royal, or the Laws could give them.</q> But the Design of that <hi>Party</hi> was to pull down the best Reformed Church in <hi>Christendom,</hi> and so they did. And altho they let in upon us an <hi>Inundation</hi> of all Opinions, Sects and Heresies (to the Scandal of all Forreign Churches, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Christianity) yet our late <hi>Pretenders to Reformation</hi> were so far from taking warning at that mischief, that they made it their business to lay all <hi>Waste</hi> and <hi>Common.</hi> For those many wise and sober Acts, which our Ancestors, with great deliberation and prudence had been contriving ever since the first Reformation, and establisht for the Security of this best of Churches, and the most Apostolical and Primitive Religion; This Party had design'd to cut them all off at one fatal blow, by a hasty <hi>Bill</hi> of some few dayes standing; which had it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken effect according to their Projection, had most infallibly blown up this Establisht and Reformed Religion; For then a <hi>Conventicle</hi> would have been planted at every Church door, to intercept and distract, nay, to divide and confound us in our Publick and Solemn Meetings. Whereupon, to my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, some of the wisest of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> do look upon the defeat of that <hi>Fanatical Party</hi> in that attempt, to be no less Miraculous for the <hi>Preservation</hi> of this Church, then his Majesties Happy <hi>Return</hi> was for the <hi>Restauration</hi> of it. And for this so Miraculous a preservation of this Church, from that Fanatical Design, next and immediately under Divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, (as far as ever I am able to understand) we are solely
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66529:10"/> obliged to thank the tender care of our most Gracious King. By which pious worthy Deed, He hath most eminently deserved, as well as justifyed, his own <hi>Title, The Defender of the Faith,</hi> and shewn himself a true <hi>Nursing-Father</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p>For those <hi>Chaplains,</hi> which were set up by this <hi>Faction,</hi> the encouragements they gave them, were not for preaching <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Righteousness,</hi> not for Propagating the <hi>Gospel,</hi> as was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, but <hi>Sedition;</hi> which how effectually they performed, He that list, may read, in the <hi>First</hi> and <hi>Second</hi> Part of the <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters Sayings,</hi> or <hi>Evangelium Armatum,</hi> to which I referr the Reader for his better satisfaction. And</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Papists,</hi> this sort of men have no such aversion to them, but upon occasion they are ready to take Sanctuary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; For Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in his first <hi>Plea,</hi> p. 233. tells us, <hi>It is but reasonable, if on such necessity they should accept of favour from any Papist that should save them (viz.</hi> from the Penalties of Conformity.) By which (sayes an ingenious Author) the Reader may judge, who is a greater friend to Popery, the <hi>Old</hi>
               <note place="margin">The second part of the Hist of Separ. <hi>P.</hi> 201.</note>
               <hi>Protestants,</hi> who have made Laws to keep it out; or the <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters,</hi> who would destroy those Laws to let it in.</p>
            <p>Now when a sober and learned Clergy have with great pains, &amp; to as great satisfaction, justifyed the present establishment of the best of Churches, in her Doctrine, Liturgy, and Government, How can they be well pleased to see a Faction (tho under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and Countenance of both Houses) so scornfully neglect a <hi>Convocation,</hi> the Legal and Signal Instrument of our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and carry on <hi>Debates</hi> about Church-Matters to such a prodigious height of extravagancy, as has exposed us more than ever, among our enemies, to the Reproach of deserting the Practice of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, to give our selves up to the <hi>Desultory Votes</hi> of a Parliament, or (which is all one) to embrace a <hi>Parliamentary-Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How violently did this Party fall upon the <hi>Synod</hi> of 1640. which consisted of as Learned and Pious men as ever met in such a Convention, and made as Prudent needful and seasonable <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> as ever were extant? <q>Poor men, sayes Dr. <hi>Heylyn,</hi> to<note place="margin">Observ. from <hi>p.</hi> 176 to 198.</note> what a distress were they brought? in danger of the Kings displeasure if they rose, of the People fury, if they sate; in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66529:10"/> danger of being beaten up by Tumults while they were at the work, of being beaten down by the following Parliament, when the work was done; and after all, obnoxious to the lash of Censorious Tongues for their good intendments. For notwithstanding their great Care, that all things might be done <hi>with decency, and to edification,</hi> every one must have his blow at them.</q> And they were encouraged hereunto by this <hi>Faction.</hi> Nor can we forget the <hi>Eleventh Persecution,</hi> (as it was called) carryed on against the most <hi>Conformable, Orthodox,</hi> and <hi>Eminent</hi> of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> with Barbarous rigour by Mr. <hi>White</hi> and his <hi>Committee,</hi> under the Parliament of <hi>Forty One.</hi> If any of those <hi>suffering</hi> Gentlemen became <hi>Enemies</hi> to Parliaments, I need not tell you who made them so; and your own Reason will tell you, they that did this, were the Parliaments first and greatest enemies; for <hi>Per quod unumquodque est tale, id Magis tale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if the <hi>Generallity,</hi> of the most Loyal and Sober <hi>Commons,</hi> have an <hi>aversion</hi> to Parliaments, 'twas the same <hi>Phanatick-par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> raised it in them. And are not they great enemies to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, who make the Constitution a terror and a grievance to the Subject. The Devil is call'd a <hi>Roaring-Lion,</hi> and a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyer;</hi> and why is he represented so <hi>terrible,</hi> but to make us hate him? we are told that <hi>Rulers are not a terror to good Works, but to the Evill: if thou dost well, be not afraid of the Power.</hi> But when the <hi>Power</hi> is set up <hi>Paramount</hi> to all Law and Equity, and they that should encourage it do make themselves a scourge to <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> they become a terror to good men and the very best of Subjects. Hereupon the Author of the<note place="margin">Vindicat of his <hi>R. H.</hi> Pag. 7.</note>
               <hi>Remarques</hi> upon <hi>Julian,</hi> tells us, <q>
                  <hi>I cannot</hi> but with Horror re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Tyrannical and Oppressive Authority which the House of <hi>Commons</hi> durst usurp over their fellow-Subjects: how many of us were persecuted by their Ban-doggs and Pursui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants? how many, that knew not so well the Charter of their Liberty, were forced to yield Obedience to their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable and peremtory votes, led in Captivity shameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly several miles through their Native Countrey up to <hi>London,</hi> Committed to illegal and chargeable prisons, harrassed with Arbitrary fines or censures, brought on their knees, forced to undergo the basest forms of submission, unworthy the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the <hi>English</hi> Liberty; and all by an usurping and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66529:11"/> Power, whom they had never offended, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst<note place="margin">pag. 3.</note> whom no offence lay! I hope, <hi>sayes He,</hi> we shall feel the scourge of such a Tyranny no more. I hope it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to that, that we of the Countrey, who send up Members to serve for us in the great Convocation of the Kingdom, shall stand in awe of the Power we trust 'em with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: I hope they are to sit there for our good and our peace: not for our terror.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And yet is it not a Common thing for the most stubborn <hi>Non-Conformists</hi> to threaten even such as are in Authority with a Parliament? and upon what account, but because they Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute them for their misdemeaners, and inflict the penalty of the Laws upon them for their disobedience? Do but check a <hi>Protestant</hi> of the <hi>New Edition,</hi> for despising Dominions and speaking evil of Dignities; and he'le tell you, we shall have a Parliament. Tax a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> tax an <hi>Associator,</hi> tax an <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noramus-Jury,</hi> tax the most malicious and injurious <hi>Republican,</hi> They'le tell you <hi>We shall have a Parliament.</hi> Is not this the way to make them a terror unto Loyalty? If we thought they would prove, what the men that use these <hi>Menaces,</hi> would have them, we should be far enough from having any fondness for their Convention. For who can have a true value for such as are set up to be a terror to their virtue. Such therefore as use these threatnings, and much more such as suggest for <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents,</hi> those matters of <hi>fact</hi> (which have been lookt upon with <hi>horror</hi> in all Ages) are to be condemned as the greatest <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> unto Parliaments.</p>
            <p>I confess, what you say is true, we should hide the naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of our Fathers, rather than expose it: <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet,</hi> received a signal Blessing for it: but that story is very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent in this Case. We are not now to treat a Patriarch, but our <hi>Representatives,</hi> in whose miscarriages we are concern'd, and so much the more, when they are committed against our King, the Father of our Countrey. Shall we see the <hi>Beacon</hi> on fire and take no notice of it? May we not enquire, when we find a Gracious King displeased, and our own expectation disappointed. May we not then enquire into the grounds of it? This sure, we are obliged to do upon a double account, that is, as well for the Justification of our selves, as for a Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to posterity. For,</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:66529:11"/>
            <p>1. Silence would argue consent; and I hope you would not have us bid them <hi>God-Speed,</hi> in their heats and violences, much less in their exorbitances against all Law, and in their notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous undutifulness to their Soveraign. In matters of Fact, when the proceedings are irregular, we must reflect upon them, that we may disown them; and we are obliged to disown them, that we may discharge our selves, and throw all the guilt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on such as have deserved it. We hope the Body of a Kingdom has as much Power and Right as you have taught a Petty Jury.</p>
            <p>2. And some care should be taken for <hi>Posterity: Dies Diem docet:</hi> We are to make the best we can of a bad market; and the best use we can make of a <hi>Past-miscarriage,</hi> is to turn it into <hi>Caution</hi> for the future. Why are <hi>Sea-marks</hi> so carefully set up and preserved, but to prevent a future <hi>Shipwrack?</hi> When we observe that such <hi>Reformado-Commonwealths-Men,</hi> or <hi>Cromwelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as have got into the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> have brought their old Seditious Principles along with them, and steer their Course (in all <hi>Debates</hi>) by their old <hi>Card</hi> and <hi>Compass,</hi> to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead others, and drive the Vessel they are imbarqued in upon <hi>Rocks and Quicksands;</hi> certainly 'its our Duty, in prudence, to take notice of it; that in future <hi>Elections</hi> of Members for that great service, we may not instead of a <hi>Worthy Patriot,</hi> make choice of an <hi>Incendiary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, in some sense, They ought not to be questioned for their freedom of Debating in the House, where matters are fit and allowed them to debate of. But it would argue too great a want of modesty to beg freedoms of speech of His Majesty, and then to take the rude Liberty to reproach him. To spit in his Face, who has given me leave to open my Mouth; every Man of common sence will condemn to be no less rude and unjust, than disingenuous and ungrateful.</p>
            <p>If therefore, they shall vent themselves in such expressions as may become Seditious, when they come to insluence the Common People, certainly if they publish them (which cannot be construed but to be to that effect) they ought not to be past over as <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent;</hi> and 'tis a signe the King has few Friends in the House, or at least, that the <hi>Major</hi> part are not his <hi>Loyal Subjects,</hi> (whatever they may pretend in words of course or comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) if they let such undutiful expressions be made <hi>Popular,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:66529:12"/> and pass the House without a censure. I am well assured, the practice was otherwise in the Reign of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and in the late Kings time, some were justly Fin'd and Imprisoned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account; for which you may see the Example of Mr. <hi>Morrice,</hi> in the account Mr. <hi>Townesend</hi> has given of the <hi>journal</hi> of Parliaments in some years of that <hi>Queens</hi> Reign, and in the Observations of Dr. <hi>Heylyn. P.</hi> 95, 96.</p>
            <p>That we should not speak evil of the Dead, has some truth and piety in it: but I do not think, the <hi>Tory-Plot-Monger</hi> takes his measures aright, when he applyes it to a dissolved Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For when the <hi>Dispute</hi> was about the Body of <hi>Moses,</hi> if the Devil cries it up so High, as to have it worshipped, I hope it is no offence to the great Law-giver to say, he was subject to <hi>Infirmities;</hi> and for all this, if the Devil will yet insist upon't, to have such honour bestow'd upon him, as is no way due to him, sure though <hi>Michael</hi> bring <hi>no rayling Accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> He may be allowed to say, <hi>The Lord Rebuke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When men die, Charity should bury their-evil Deeds with them. But if fond and superstitious men will <hi>Canonize</hi> their <hi>Memory</hi> so far as to make their very Errours, and the very worst of Actions become precedents, 'tis no <hi>Sin</hi> but <hi>Duty</hi> to call them to remembrance, and <hi>remarke</hi> them to Posterity.</p>
            <p>Sir, I beg your pardon, in that I had almost forgot the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Soveraignty you mention, tho indeed 'tis scarce worth the remembring: Whatever the <hi>Late</hi> Practice of that <hi>Party</hi> hath assum'd, if I mistake not, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath been the <hi>Principal</hi> Herauld at Armes that has proclaimed it, (and he is audacious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to publish any thing.)</p>
            <p>I confess there is a <hi>Soveraignty</hi> in Parliament, as it is the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Court</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> But when we speak of the two <hi>Houses,</hi> and much more, if we speak of the <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>distinction</hi> from, and opposition to the King, there is no such Soveraignty belongs to them.</p>
            <p>The Statute of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c. 21. saith thus, in the pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it, <hi>Whereas His Majesties Realm Recognizeth no Superiour under God, but only His Majesty.</hi> If the whole Realm <hi>recognize</hi> no other Superiour, do <hi>They,</hi> by their <hi>Election</hi> of Members for Parliament, set up so many new Soveraigns over Themselves? Is the whole Realm under the King as their only Superiour,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66529:12"/> and are their <hi>Representatives,</hi> presently, <hi>Hail-Fellow-Well-met,</hi> with his Majesty? Who sends abroad <hi>Ambassadors?</hi> Who makes <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Warr?</hi> But we need not travel from home for <hi>Marks</hi> of Soveraignty: Who has the command of the <hi>Militia</hi> by Sea and Land? How come the two Houses to sit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether? Do they sign <hi>Warrants</hi> with their own <hi>Signets</hi> to Summon or Dissolve <hi>Themselves?</hi> No, these are marks of the Kings <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and a branch of His <hi>Royal</hi> Soveraignty, which the House of <hi>Commons</hi> share as little in as they which sent them; which is <hi>not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are told, that King <hi>James</hi> once said in a time of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, (but whether in way of <hi>jear,</hi> or otherwise, who can tell,) <q>That there were now five hunded Kings besides himself. Tho great advantage have been made of those words, yet to any man that rightly understands the constitution of an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Parliament, the <hi>Commons</hi> are so far from being either<note place="margin">Observat. <hi>pag.</hi> 58.</note> Lords or Kings, that (Dr. <hi>Heylyn</hi> affirms) they are not so much, as a part of the <hi>Supream-Councel;</hi> it being easy (saith He) to be evidenced out of the <hi>Writ,</hi> which commands their attendance,</q> that they are called only to <hi>consent</hi> and <hi>submit</hi> to such Resolutions and Conclusions as should be then and there agreed on by the Kings great Councel, or the great Councel of the Kingdom. The word of the Writ import no more.<note place="margin">The power of the Lords and Commons, <hi>pr.</hi> 1680.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ad faciendum &amp; Consentiendum his, quae tum ibidem de Communi consilio dicti Regni nostri (favente Deo) contigerit Ordinari.</hi> Before <hi>Henry</hi> the 3d. all <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> passed by the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Peers.</hi> In point of Judicature, the Judgment belongs to the Lords only, saith Mr. <hi>Selden:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Of the Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam. <hi>p.</hi> 132 &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 133.</note> and the House of Commons disclaim'd it (1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7th.) by Solemn Protestation. Nay He tells us fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, That <hi>They</hi> had no Power formerly to judge of the <hi>Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of their <hi>own</hi> Members. <note n="†" place="margin">Ib. <hi>p.</hi> 10.</note> And perhaps, since there has been such <hi>factions</hi> and violent stickling to make <hi>Parties,</hi> it were hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py for the Government, if that were the practice at this Day. And how came this Change? Doubtless as the <hi>Tares</hi> came into the Field: The <hi>Crafty</hi> Enemy did it while men slept.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Supremacy</hi> should be divided betwixt the Two <hi>Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> is a <hi>Riddle</hi> to me, and that the Power of the Commons should be <hi>Coordinate</hi> with His Majesties, much more. Are they not His Subjects when they enter into the House? How come
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66529:13"/> they to put off their Subjection? Does their <hi>Priviledge</hi> exalt them presently <hi>above all that is called</hi> God (by creation and office) and all that is <hi>Civilly</hi> worshipped upon that account? In their <hi>Personal Capacities</hi> we know they are all but Subjects: They all swear <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the King, and if they Act other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, they are all <hi>forsworn</hi> before God; and when he calls them to Accompt he will judge them so. Grant them to be the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentatives</hi> of all the <hi>Commons,</hi> and in that sence the <hi>Body</hi> of them; yet they must have a <hi>Head;</hi> and if so, yet still they are <hi>Subordinate.</hi> If their <hi>Conjunction</hi> gives them a <hi>share</hi> in the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, at what <hi>Period</hi> of time, by what <hi>Form</hi> of words, or <hi>Symbolical Ceremonies</hi> is that Power derived to them? Why are the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy</hi> tendred to them at their entrance of the House, but on purpose to prevent that surmise? And when they are most and best <hi>Ʋnited</hi> in the House, why do they, in all their <hi>Addresses</hi> to His Majesty, stile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves His most <hi>Loyal</hi> and most <hi>Humble Subjects?</hi> They should take the Title of His <hi>Partners</hi> and <hi>Associates</hi> in the <hi>Royal Power</hi> if they were <hi>Coordinate:</hi> But the Name of Subjects, and <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Obedient Subjects:</hi> in their Addresses, is an utter <hi>disclaimer</hi> of all pretence to such a <hi>Coordinate Power</hi> and share in the <hi>Soveraignty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For their pretence to the <hi>Legislative Power,</hi> there is a great deal more made of it, than it will amount unto. Without the Kings Royal Assent, no Law can be made or changed. And without His Assent, no Orders or Ordinances of one or both the Houses (of <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi>) can be good, to make or change Laws. And this Prerogative of the King (saith Mr. <hi>Shepperd</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Tit Prerog in Parl. <hi>p.</hi> 5.</note> in his <hi>Abridgement</hi>) is not grantable over to any other, (whereas the Power of <hi>Judicature</hi> is communicable.)</p>
            <p>The Houses, you say, have a <hi>Hand</hi> in the <hi>Legislation:</hi> So hath the <hi>Beggar</hi> in my <hi>Almes.</hi>
               <q>When a thing is said to be<note place="margin">Remains <hi>p.</hi> 59.</note> enacted by the King, with the advice and assent of the two Houses, That <hi>Advice</hi> and <hi>Assent</hi> of the two Houses is their passing and enacting of it, <hi>as to their Part,</hi> saith the Lord <hi>Hollis.</hi>
               </q> For to speak properly, No man has a Legislative Power, <hi>Originally,</hi> but he whose <hi>Will</hi> is a Law; I say <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally;</hi> for in process of time, and upon emergent <hi>Compacts, Customs</hi> and <hi>Consent,</hi> the Constitution may be otherwise. And so it is said, in the <hi>Preamble</hi> of the Statute of 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. 21.
<q>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:66529:13"/> That this Realm is free from Subjection to any Mans Laws, but only such as have been devised, made and ordained within this Realm for the weal of the same, or to such others as by the Sufferance of the King and his Progenitors, the People of this Realm, have taken at their free Liberty by their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, to be used among them, and have bound themselves by long Custom to the observance of the same.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But, as I was saying, Originally none has a Legislative Power, but he whose <hi>Will</hi> is a <hi>Law.</hi> And this is the purport of that <hi>Trite</hi> saying among the <hi>Civilians, Quod principi placuit legis ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet vigorem:</hi> The Princes pleasure hath the Force of a Law; and this appears from the manner of making Laws amongst us, <hi>Le Roy leveut:</hi> The King Wills it shall be so: And this <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of the King's pleasure passeth it into a Law.</p>
            <p>This is the King's Will <hi>fix'd</hi> and <hi>bounded;</hi> and it is in this sence, that <hi>Bracton</hi> saith, <hi>Rex in Regno suo Superiores habet Deum &amp; legem:</hi> The King in his Realm hath two Superiours, <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Law.</hi> For when the <hi>King</hi>'s Will is <hi>fixt</hi> by a standing Law, that Law becomes, in some sence, Superiour to Him: That is, His <hi>Deliberate</hi> and <hi>Fixed</hi> Will is preferrable and Superiour to that which is but <hi>Transient</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary.</hi> And thus, having made a <hi>Grant</hi> of any thing, and tyed up our own Hands by that Means; 'tis an usual saying with us, That such a thing <hi>is not in our power;</hi> because we have already made it over for the benefit of another, and it is become His <hi>Right,</hi> which (then) we cannot divest Him of without His own Consent.</p>
            <p>Having laid down this, I shall give my Reasons, why the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gislative power</hi> cannot properly be attributed to the Two Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Because every Law is an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> in the Prince; and an <hi>Act of Grace</hi> it must needs be, because it is a <hi>restraint</hi> of his Will, and a <hi>bounding</hi> of his Prerogative. <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dignatur ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere de jure suo Regio.</hi> And he passes Acts <hi>non ex debito justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> but <hi>ex Gratia.</hi> See <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid.</hi> of <hi>Britain.</hi> pag. 108. &amp;c.</note> Hereupon the Preface to <hi>Magna Charta</hi> runs thus; <hi>Henry,</hi> by the Grace of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Know you, that We <hi>of our meer and free Will</hi> have given and Granted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What is an Act of Grace in the Prince, cannot be an Act of Power in the Subject; for that would confound Prince and Subject; which is irrational, inconsistent, and absurd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Houses <hi>properly</hi> have no share in the <hi>Legislative power;</hi> because they obtain our Laws <hi>by prayer.</hi> In making of our Antient Laws, saith Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> The Commons did <hi>petere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ʋbi Sup.</hi> p. 132.</note> the Lords <hi>Assentire,</hi> and the King <hi>Concludere.</hi> The <hi>Commons</hi> did
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66529:14"/>
               <hi>Pray,</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> did <hi>Assent,</hi> the <hi>King Conclude.</hi> The Lords did <hi>Assent,</hi> not to the <hi>Law;</hi> for it is no Law when it is brought to them for their <hi>Assent:</hi> But to the <hi>Petition</hi> of the Commons, to be made a Law; and the Lords <hi>Assent</hi> unto it, as a thing that will tend to the Honour of the Crown (whereof they are, or should be the <hi>Guardians</hi>) as well as to the Benefit of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, whom the House of Commons Represents; and on whose behalf they do Petition.</p>
            <p>Now if the <hi>Petitioner,</hi> tho' never so highly recommended, obtains his Request, yet 'tis very <hi>Catacrestical</hi> to call him his own <hi>Almoner</hi> upon that account; and tho' he reaps the profit of it, yet to allow him a share in the <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Grant</hi> of the Benefaction, would be a great <hi>Derogation</hi> to the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Generosity</hi> of the Benefactor.</p>
            <p>That this is the Case in making of Laws, besides Mr. <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>'s Authority, we have the Stile of our Laws at this day to justify it. In the 13 <hi>Car. 2. c.</hi> 1. The Act runs thus: We, the Lords and Commons in Parliament Assembled, do most humbly beseech Your most excellent Majesty, <hi>That it may be Enacted</hi> (This is the Lords and Commons part) <hi>And be it Enacted by the Kings Most Excellent Majesty:</hi> This is <hi>Le Roy leveut,</hi> the King's <hi>Fiat</hi> to it, which gives it the Authority and Force of a Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another Argument against their having an (<hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative</hi>) hand in the <hi>Legislation</hi> is this: No <hi>Legislator,</hi> that is, no <hi>Soveraign</hi> is under the <hi>Coercive</hi> Power of his own Law. But if the Lords and Commons, or any of them shall commit Felony or Treason; Will their <hi>Membership,</hi> or pretended <hi>Soveraignty</hi> give them a priviledge, and exempt them from Prosecution? I trow not. Why do they beg freedom to Debate when they enter the House, if they were not liable, both to miscarriage, and to be question'd for it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I will conclude this with one Instance, which I am sure is unanswerable. If they have a <hi>Legislative Power</hi> in all Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, then in <hi>An Act of pardon and oblivion.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">13 <hi>Carol. 2. c.</hi> 1. They Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it, His Majesties incomparable Grace and Goodness to His People.</note> Do the Lords and Commons (<hi>Authoritatively</hi>) make this? then they Pardon <hi>Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves;</hi> which is a greater Power than any <hi>Priest</hi> or <hi>Pope</hi> did ever yet pretend to.</p>
            <p>But we are to inquire what is to be done to recover that <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> which hath been ever paid to these Antient and Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Constitutions? Certainly Parliaments can never do them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves more Right and Honour, then in bringing such <hi>Seditious
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66529:14"/> Politico'es</hi> to condign Punishment; for till such <hi>Principles</hi> be rooted out of our <hi>Politicks,</hi> neither Prince nor Loyal Subject can be safe; nor indeed can the Government stand secure; For such Maximes will not only Countenance but <hi>Legitimate</hi> any Faction (if they can make Head and get strength enough) to Subvert it: But that is not All.</p>
            <p>To do as we would be done by, if we were in the same Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, is a Rule that will go far, and hold good to all Relations. And there is Another no less Authentick: <hi>Render unto</hi> Caesar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caesar's, <hi>and to</hi> God <hi>the things that are</hi> God's.</p>
            <p>The things of <hi>God</hi> are <hi>Deposited</hi> in His Church; and <hi>Hear the Church,</hi> saith our Blessed Saviour. The Church is <hi>The Ground and Pillar of Truth</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 14, 15.</note> in <hi>England,</hi> as well as it was at <hi>Ephesus,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 3.</note> where <hi>Timothy</hi> presided, as <hi>Metropolitan.</hi> This Church (of <hi>England</hi>) tho' overwhelmed awhile with an <hi>Inundation</hi> of <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies,</hi> yet (all the while) stood firm under Water (as a Rock) till those Floods were dryed up or stagnated in <hi>Conventicles.</hi> And they will flow again into the <hi>Bosome</hi> of the Church, or sink into the Earth, and come to nothing.</p>
            <p>Hear the Church therefore, as She speaks to you, upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, in <hi>Synods,</hi> or (which is all one) in <hi>Convocations:</hi> Hear <hi>Her</hi> in her <hi>Doctrine;</hi> Hear <hi>Her</hi> in her <hi>Liturgies,</hi> wherein She speaks to you continually; &amp; Hear Her in her <hi>Discipline,</hi> wherein She is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to speak to you, as soon as you are ready to give Her <hi>Audience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was Resolved by the House of <hi>Commons</hi> in the Parliament at <hi>Westminster, Jan.</hi> 10. 1680.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is the Opinion of this House, That the Prosecution of</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant <hi>Dissenters upon the penal Laws, is at this time, grievous to the Subject, a weakning of the</hi> Protestant <hi>Interest, an encouragement to</hi> Popery, <hi>and dangerous to the Peace of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Vote</hi> did not tend to Heal or Unite, but much more to break and scatter us: And the <hi>Jesuites</hi> (who have their <hi>Speaking-Trumpets</hi> in our <hi>Conventicles,</hi> to suggest such Doctrine at a distance) will thank them for it.</p>
            <p>To restore Parliaments to their due and antient Veneration, They must give God his <hi>Due,</hi> which He demands of us by His Church: And <hi>Caesar</hi> must have his Due too. If any encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therefore has been made upon the Crown, let Parliaments take care to redress it. For we shall never be at ease and quiet, till we be reduced to our primitive Constitutions. If it can be truly said, <hi>Ab initio non fuit sic,</hi> from the beginning it was not so, then we must come to that Rule, What is Written in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66529:15"/> Law? How readest thou? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <note n="*" place="margin">Conc. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen. Can. 6.</note> Let old Customs be kept; In this case, <hi>As you were,</hi> the Souldiers <hi>Posture,</hi> will be the best for our <hi>Defence</hi> and <hi>Safety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In our <hi>Magna-Charta,</hi> it is ordered that no Freeman be <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merced,</hi> but <hi>salvo contenemento suo;</hi> What <hi>Contenement</hi> signifies is some question: but that it signifies some useful and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable thing, that belongs to him is out of all question, <hi>Ne suo honorabili Contenemento amittet;</hi> saith <hi>Glanvil.</hi> The Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides<note place="margin">† On <hi>Magna Chart.</hi> cap. 14.</note> that he loseth not this advantage, (whatsoever it be.) Sr. <hi>E. Cooke</hi> saith, it signifies a mans <hi>Countenance</hi> which he hath together with, and by reason of, his <hi>Freehold.</hi> And they say, the <hi>Armour</hi> of a <hi>Souldier,</hi> and the <hi>Books</hi> of a <hi>Schollar,</hi> as well as the <hi>Wainage</hi> of a <hi>Villein,</hi> (which is named in the Charter) are their countenances.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Books</hi> are not more needful for a <hi>Schollar,</hi> nor <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi> for a <hi>Souldier,</hi> than His Prerogative is for the King: He cannot Govern the Realm, He cannot defend Himself, He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enforce the Laws, He cannot protect the just, nor punish e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil doers, without it. If we allow him to have any <hi>Freehold,</hi> His Prerogative is his <hi>Contenement,</hi> the very countenance of his Majesty; and if it were not for that, <hi>He</hi> and <hi>We</hi> should be at a loss in a thousand Accidents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salus populi suprema Lex,</hi> was the old saying, <hi>The safety of the people is the supreme Law:</hi> but it is not the peoples Law, nor, are they to be entrusted with the execution of it. 'Tis the <hi>Royal-Law,</hi> which the Prince prescribes unto <hi>Himself;</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that <hi>safety</hi> of the People does consist, and by what <hi>means</hi> and <hi>methods</hi> it is to be preserved, is in the Princes breast to determine. But it cannot be performed, or effectually provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, without his Prerogative. And therefore tis not usual with God Himself to take any <hi>Amerciament</hi> of a Prince, but <hi>Salvo contenemento,</hi> (as we see in the signal example of <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi>) <note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 4. 36.</note> and I am sure 'tis the Subjects Duty to be as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the Kings Interest as he is of theirs; That the <hi>English-Liberties</hi> may not devour the <hi>English-Monarchy;</hi> And whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Princes grant, 'tis with this Exception, Of impeaching His Prerogatives, as is to be seen in the Statute of <hi>Westminster. For as much as the King hath ordained these things,</hi> (viz. this Stat. of <hi>West.</hi> 1.) <hi>for the honour of God and the Church, and for the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>West.</hi> 1. 48. 3. E. 1.</note>
               <hi>Common-Weal, and for remedy of such as are grieved, He would not that at any other time it should turn in prejudice of him, or of his Crown, but that such right as appertain to him should be saved in all points.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:66529:15"/>
            <p>These (as the Lawyers tell us) are some <q>Branches of the<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Shep,</hi> Abridg, <hi>tit.</hi> Prerog. <hi>pag.</hi> 56.</note> Kings Prerogative, 1. That generally <hi>Statutes of Restraint,</hi> be they in the affirmative or negative, do not bind him, unless he be expresly named: or it be a Statute to <hi>Advance Religion,</hi> suppress fraud, or other wickedness.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>2. That in the construction of a Statute, nothing is to be taken by equity against the King.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>3. That he shall have Advantage by an <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> tho he be not named in it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>4. That he is favoured in the exposition of any Statute.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>5. That where an <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> gives any thing to him by the name of King, this generally shall inure to Him and his Successors; so that every King shall have it after him.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It might very well become the duty of a Parliament, (as well as the Generosity of the <hi>English</hi> Nation) &amp; would tend much to the redeeming of their Honour, To restore what has been clipt off the Crown by surprize or fraud; and return what has been taken from the Prerogative by <hi>Duress,</hi> or thrown o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-board upon the violence of some <hi>Storm,</hi> or stress of Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For, if as all <q>
                  <hi>Casuists</hi> hold, those Oaths and Promises which are extorted by fear or force, are not obligatory; I cannot tell why those things which by meer necessity Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are compel'd to, as well for the preservation of their Body Natural as Politick, should be denyed the priviledg of being dissolved upon that very score, that other things of the same Nature are; as is very well argued by the Author of <hi>The great point of Succession Discussed,</hi> page 22.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In a Monarchy of this Complexion, great care should be taken to keep the Ballance even; For in <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. his time: when the Lords were grown too High, it was found and felt, <hi>Quot Domini tot Tyranni:</hi> So many Lords so many Tyrants; And may not the <hi>Commons</hi> grow so great and insolent too, as to <hi>Lord</hi> over the Prince and Nobles. There can be no doubt of this to such as can remember the proceedings of that Faction, which sprang up in the House of <hi>Commons</hi> in 41. Sr. <hi>Edw. Deering</hi> in the <hi>Collection of his Speeches, tells us, That, If they could bring the Lords to sit in the House of Commons, and the King to be but as one of the Lords, then their work was done.</hi> And what that was (which was driven home with a witness at last) some of the Noble <hi>Peers</hi> have as little reason to forget as his <hi>Majesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It concerns us therefore to strengthen the Kings hands, that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66529:16"/> he may be able to Govern and Hold the <hi>Ballance</hi> even; Else when there are <hi>Factions</hi> got into both Houses, and the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> contend who shall sway the <hi>Beam;</hi> they will jostle the <hi>scales</hi> one against another (as they have done too often in our memory) and we shall never be at quiet betwixt them.</p>
            <p>But whom may we trust to accomplish so great as well as needful a Work? All <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and <hi>Freeholders,</hi> are concern'd to be inquisitive, and careful that they be not imposed upon, and take false measures.</p>
            <p>There are a Generation of men, who have not only a froward <hi>Indignation</hi> against the Persons of their Prince and Governour, but an <hi>Aversiou</hi> to the Government it self. This <hi>Antipathy,</hi> and Distemper many times is <hi>Haereditary,</hi> and, like some diseases <hi>Runs in a Blood,</hi> through whole Families; take special heed of such men. For 'tis their Inclination, they have ever don't, and they will ever seek occasion to Embroile us.</p>
            <p>Take heed of such as are <hi>Discontented</hi> at their <hi>Disappointments</hi> in the pursuit of their designs of Avarice or Ambition; These Commonly are <hi>Murmurers</hi> and <hi>Complainers;</hi> and 'tis a part of their Character (as well as practice hereupon). They separate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, or have a kindness for separation, and therefore are not very like to Unite us. They are mainly in love with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties and changes, and can hold to nothing that is well setled. How many formes and shapes did they change into, in the late times? New formes of Confessions, of Catechisms, of Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, in the Church; till we had not the face of a Church left amongst us. And what changes and formes had we in the Civil State? Instead of King and Parliament of the old Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Constitution, we had a Parliament without Bishops, then without and against the <hi>King,</hi> without <hi>Lords;</hi> and at last one made up of a <hi>Rump</hi> of <hi>Commons;</hi> we were under <hi>Keepers</hi> of our <hi>Liberties,</hi> till we had none left to help our selves; at last we were enthrald under the Arbitrary Power of a <hi>Protector</hi> and his <hi>Mercenary</hi> Army. And to this pass, That <hi>Society</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <hi>Jesuites,</hi> did designe to reduce us, as is clear in the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> of their late <hi>Association.</hi> We have paid dear for our skill in Ringing such Changes; which I hope will teach us to take the <hi>Wise-mans</hi> Caution, <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to Change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take heed of such as have <hi>Feather'd</hi> their <hi>Nests</hi> heretofore, with Crown and Church-Lands; who have parted with their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66529:16"/> Prince and their Religion to purchase the <hi>Revenues,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to them; For these having been stript of their unjust <hi>Acquists</hi> by the happy <hi>Restauration</hi> of the King and Church, they will Study to embroile us, if not to recover their lost <hi>Booty,</hi> yet at least to be revenged on the Right Propriators.</p>
            <p>Beware of your Subtile <hi>Politicians,</hi> who will <hi>shift</hi> their <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> to gratify a <hi>Party</hi> for their own Ends; For they that can part with Religion and Conscience upon such unworthy Termes, will never stick to Sacrifice their King and Countrey to their Interest. And the <hi>Atheist,</hi> who is under no awe of a <hi>Deity,</hi> or <hi>the Powers of the World to Come,</hi> He makes Religion nothing but a <hi>Reason of State</hi> to govern fooles; and He will be sure, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than run any hazard, to do the like.</p>
            <p>And there are a Sett of <hi>Pragmatical,</hi> jealous and designing <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots,</hi> who are better skil'd at Creating plots and dangers, than at suppressing or preventing them. These have their Arts to inflame the people's passions, that they may have the honour to allay them at the Charge of the Kings Prerogative. These are generally <hi>Partial</hi> in their <hi>Conformity,</hi> and make choice of a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Religion; not to save their Souls, but to inhance their Reputation, and serve their factious interest. They are not <hi>Ʋniform</hi> in their obedience; but while they pretend to <hi>abhor Idols,</hi> they will make no scruple to <hi>Commit Sacriledge.</hi> They will Court you as your humble Servant, and cut your throat for their own Ends, and the <hi>Good Old Cause</hi> shall bear them out in it.</p>
            <p>I must Caution these Gentlemen likewise against <hi>Raw</hi> and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant <hi>Novices,</hi> who may follow the <hi>Cry</hi> of a <hi>Factious</hi> Party, but want <hi>Sagacity</hi> to take the <hi>Sent</hi> of Truth and Justice. I have known some of these, who have resolv'd to <hi>Ʋote</hi> down divers things, which afterward, (when the <hi>Fit</hi> of Reforming was aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) they have Confessed they did not understand. Such as these will prove <hi>Physicians of no value;</hi> They are not skil'd in the <hi>Pulse,</hi> or Constitution of the <hi>Body Politick;</hi> They may be for violent <hi>Purgings, Amputations,</hi> or <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> as if the <hi>Body</hi> were affected with a <hi>Calenture</hi> or a <hi>Gangrene,</hi> when the Distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is nothing else but the <hi>Spleen</hi> or a <hi>Flatus</hi> of <hi>Fanaticisme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such as have drawn their Sword against their Prince, no doubt, they have learnt the Rule of their Master <hi>Machiavel,</hi> and cast away their <hi>Scabbard.</hi> These Persons are to be lookt upon as having the traiterous and bloody <hi>Blade</hi> still naked in their hands, ready, if occasion serves, for assault and execution.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66529:17"/> Who therefore are by no means to be imployed in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Peace, which are to be transacted with all imaginable Calmness. And if the Law does not allow such as <hi>Trade</hi> in Blood (tho it be but in the blood of <hi>Animals</hi>) to be impanneld upon any <hi>Jury,</hi> wherein life is concern'd, How can it consist with the Prudence of the Nation, to entrust such as have served a <hi>Voluntary</hi> Apprentiship in <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and glutted themselves with the blood of their Prince and his Loyal Subjects, to Consult about the Termes of our common Safety, or Act towards the Settlement of our Tranquillity? But there are <hi>true Sons of the Church of England,</hi> who pay a strict and constant observance to all the commands of their Ghostly Mother, who have a great Veneration for the Crown, the Laws and Government, and look upon the Person and Majesty of their Prince as Highly <hi>Sacred;</hi> such men (chosen for our <hi>Representatives</hi>) would study <hi>Religiously</hi> to bring us to a present <hi>Ʋnion</hi> and Settlement.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, His <hi>Gracious Majesty</hi> hath offered very fair towards it; and if the <hi>Subjects</hi> would carefully, in their <hi>Respec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Stations,</hi> perform their <hi>Duty,</hi> there would be little reason for <hi>Complaining in our Streets.</hi> When his Majesty (as much as is possible) endeavours <hi>to see with his own Eyes,</hi> and <hi>hear with his own Eares,</hi> that He may not be surprized to pass Acts either to the <hi>Prejudice</hi> of his good Subjects, or his own Prerogative; when His <hi>Officers</hi> are persons of great <hi>Skill</hi> for their employments, and of known <hi>Integrity;</hi> when the Laws are <hi>duely put in Execution;</hi> when <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Punishments,</hi> are equally distributed to <hi>Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> Virtue and <hi>Correct</hi> Vice; what can we desire more?</p>
            <p>The rest lyes on our part, let us lay aside our <hi>Factions</hi> and <hi>Animosities:</hi> let us learn to love the <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor <hi>Schisme, Sedition,</hi> and <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> as much as we pretend to hate <hi>Idolatry:</hi> let us believe Almighty-God, That, <hi>To obey, is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than Sacrifice:</hi> and let our <hi>Practice</hi> be according to that <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe;</hi> let us make use of <hi>Religion,</hi> not to make our selves po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular, and purchase a baneful Reputation, but to advance Gods Glory; not to <hi>save</hi> our Estates, but our Souls: let us frequent the <hi>Church</hi> (and attend to all her Administrations) as the best <hi>School</hi> of Vertue, and the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> of Devout &amp; Pious Souls; then may we sing <hi>In convertendo,</hi> and rejoyce in the happy return of our Prosperity; Wherein I can Rest with very great Contentment.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <lb/>
               <signed>Your Humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>